<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<merger version="3"><dataSet config="main$Generated" generated="true"><source path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res"/><source path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\build\generated\res\rs\debug"/><source path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\build\generated\res\resValues\debug"/></dataSet><dataSet config="debug$Generated" generated="true"><source path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\debug\res"/></dataSet><dataSet config="main" generated-set="main$Generated"><source path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res"><file name="backgrounds" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-hdpi\backgrounds.jpg" qualifiers="hdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="consumer" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-hdpi\consumer.jpg" qualifiers="hdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="customers" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-hdpi\customers.jpeg" qualifiers="hdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="def" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-hdpi\def.jpg" qualifiers="hdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="help" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-hdpi\help.jpeg" qualifiers="hdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="hises" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-hdpi\hises.jpg" qualifiers="hdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="ic_launcher" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-hdpi\ic_launcher.png" qualifiers="hdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="images1" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-hdpi\images1.jpeg" qualifiers="hdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="introduction" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-hdpi\introduction.jpg" qualifiers="hdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="mainload" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-hdpi\mainload.jpg" qualifiers="hdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="mainloadingsss" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-hdpi\mainloadingsss.jpg" qualifiers="hdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="ref" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-hdpi\ref.jpeg" qualifiers="hdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="ic_launcher" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-mdpi\ic_launcher.png" qualifiers="mdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="ic_launcher" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-xhdpi\ic_launcher.png" qualifiers="xhdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="ic_launcher" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\drawable-xxhdpi\ic_launcher.png" qualifiers="xxhdpi-v4" type="drawable"/><file name="activity_main" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\layout\activity_main.xml" qualifiers="" type="layout"/><file name="activity_number_five" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\layout\activity_number_five.xml" qualifiers="" type="layout"/><file name="activity_number_four" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\layout\activity_number_four.xml" qualifiers="" type="layout"/><file name="activity_number_one" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\layout\activity_number_one.xml" qualifiers="" type="layout"/><file name="activity_number_six" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\layout\activity_number_six.xml" qualifiers="" type="layout"/><file name="activity_number_three" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\layout\activity_number_three.xml" qualifiers="" type="layout"/><file name="activity_number_two" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\layout\activity_number_two.xml" qualifiers="" type="layout"/><file name="activity_second" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\layout\activity_second.xml" qualifiers="" type="layout"/><file name="main" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\menu\main.xml" qualifiers="" type="menu"/><file name="number_five" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\menu\number_five.xml" qualifiers="" type="menu"/><file name="number_four" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\menu\number_four.xml" qualifiers="" type="menu"/><file name="number_one" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\menu\number_one.xml" qualifiers="" type="menu"/><file name="number_six" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\menu\number_six.xml" qualifiers="" type="menu"/><file name="number_three" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\menu\number_three.xml" qualifiers="" type="menu"/><file name="number_two" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\menu\number_two.xml" qualifiers="" type="menu"/><file name="second" path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\menu\second.xml" qualifiers="" type="menu"/><file path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\values\dimens.xml" qualifiers=""><dimen name="activity_horizontal_margin">16dp</dimen><dimen name="activity_vertical_margin">16dp</dimen></file><file path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\values\strings.xml" qualifiers=""><string name="action_settings">Settings</string><string name="title_activity_number_five">Help</string><string name="help"><u>Consumer Disputes Redressal Forums (District Forum)</u> :\n\n
 Claims less than or equal Rs.20 lacs . \n\n

<u>Consumer Disputes Redressal Commissions   (State Commission)</u> : \n\n
Claim more than Rs.20 lacs &amp; less than Rs.1 crore &amp; appeals.\n\n

<u>National Consumer Disputes Redressal Commission (National Commission)</u> :\n\n 
Claim equal to Rs.1 crore &amp; appeals\n\n--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</string><string name="title_activity_second">Consumer Protection Rights</string><string name="complain">An aggrieved consumer seeks redressal under the Act through the instrumentality of complaint. It does not mean that the consumer can complain against his each and every problem. The Act has provided certain grounds on which complaint can be made. Similarly, relief against these complaints can be granted within the set pattern.\n\n

<u>What constitutes a complaint </u> : [Section 2(1)(c)] - Complaint is a statement made in writing to the National Commission, the State Commission or the District Forum by a person competent to file it, containing the allegations in detail, and with a view to obtain relief provided under the Act.\n\n

<u>Who can file a complaint</u> :[Sections 2(b) &amp; 12] - At the outset it is clear that a person who can be termed as a consumer under the Act can make a complaint. To be specific on this account, following are the persons who can file a complaint under the Act : \n\n
(a) a consumer; or \n\n
(b) any voluntary consumer association registered under the Companies Act, 1956 or under any other law for the time being in force, or \n\n
(c) the Central Government or any State Government, \n\n
(d) one or more consumers, where there are numerious consumers having the same interest.\n\n

<u>What a complaint must contain</u> : [Section 2(1)(c)] - A complaint must contain any of the following allegations :\n\n
(a) An unfair trade practice or a restrictive trade practice has been adopted by any trader \n\n

Example : A sold a six months old car to B representing it to be a new one. Here B can make a complaint against A for following an unfair trade practice. \n\n

(b) The goods bought by him or agreed to be bought by him suffer from one or more defects;\n\n

<u>Example</u> : A bought a computer from B. It was not working properly since day one. A can make a complaint against B for supplying him a defective computer.\n\n

(c) The services hired or availed of or agreed to be hired or availed of by him suffer from deficiency in any respect.\n\n

<u>Example</u> : A hired services of an advocate to defend himself against his landlord. The advocate did not appear every time the case was scheduled. A can make a complaint against the advocate.\n\n


<u>Time frame within which a complaint can be filed</u> : Section 24A of the Act provides that a consumer dispute can be filed within two years from the date on which the cause of action arises. Since this provision was inserted in the Act in 1993, before that the Consumer Forums were following the Limitation Act, 1963, which says that a suit can be filed within three years after the cause of action arises.\n\n

<u>Examples</u> :A got his eye operated by B in 1989. He got a certificate of blindness on 18th December, 1989. He was still in hope of gaining his sight and went from second operation in 1992 and was discharged on 21-1-1992. He filed a complaint against B on 11-1-1994. B opposed on the ground that more than 2 years were over after 18-12-1989, thus the complaint is not maintainable. The Commission held that here the cause of action for filing the complaint would arose after the second operation when A lost entire hope of recovery.\n\n

<u>Relief available against complain</u> : [Sections 14 and 22] - A complainan can seek any one or more of the following relief under the Act:2.11 consumer protection act Para 1.3:\n\n

(a) to remove the defect pointed out by the appropriate laboratory from the goods in question;
(b) to replace the goods with new goods of similar description which shall be free from any defect;
(c) to return to the complainant the price, or, as the case may be, the charges paid by the complainant;
(d) to pay such amount as may be awarded by it as compensation to the consumer for any loss or injury suffered by the consumer due to the negligence of the opposite party;
(e) to remove the defects or deficiencies in the services in question;
(f) to discontinue the unfair trade practice or the restrictive trade practice or not to repeat it;
(g) not to offer the hazardous goods for sale;
(h) to withdraw the hazardous goods from being offered for sale;
(i) to provide from adequate costs to complainant.\n\n

<u>When a complaint cannot be filed </u> : A complaint on behalf of the public which consists of unidentifiable consumers cannot be filed under the Act. \n\n

<u>Example</u> : A complaint was filed on the basis of a newspaper report that passengers travelling by flight No. 1C-401 from Calcutta to Delhi on May 13,1989 were made to stay at the airport and the flight was delayed by 90 minutes causing great inconvenience to the passengers. It was held that such a general complaint cannot be entertained. No passenger who boarded that plane came forward or authorised the complainant to make the complaint .

<u>Dismissal of frivolous and vexatious complaints</u> : - Since the Act provides for an inexpensive procedure (Court fees is not charged in consumer Para 1.4 consumer protection act 2.12 complaints under the Act) for filing complaints, there is a possibility that the Act is misused by people for filing vexations claims. To discourage frivolous and vexatious claims, the Act has provided that such complaints will be dismissed and the complainant can be charged with the costs not exceeding Rs. 10,000.\n\n

<u>Example</u> : A filed a complaint against B to recover compensation of Rs. 55,99,000 with the motive of indulging in speculative litigation taking undue advantage of the fact that no court fee was payable under the Consumer Protection Act. The National Commission held that the complainant has totally failed to make a case against B, and dismissed the complaint as frivolous and vexatious imposing Rs. 10,000 as costs to A.\n\n

<u>Essential Information during filing Complain</u> : \n\n

Name and full address of complainant\n\n
Name and full address of opposite party\n\n
Description of goods and services\n\n
Quality and quantity\n\n
Price\n\n
Date &amp; proof of purchase\n\n
Nature of deception\n\n
Type of redressal prayed for\n\n--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</string><string name="cus"><u>Two kinds of consumer under the Act </u>: \n\n

<u>Consumer of goods</u> : buys or agrees to buy goods or any user of such goods. \n\n

<u>Examples</u> : A purchased a scooter which was in B’s possession from the date of 
purchase. B was using it and taking it to the seller for repairs and service from
time to time. Later on B had a complaint regarding the scooter. He sued the
seller. The seller pleaded that since B did not buy the scooter, he was not a con-
sumer under the Act. The Delhi State Commission held that B, the complainant
was using it with the approval of A, the buyer, and therefore he was consumer
under the Act. \n\n

<u>Consumer of services</u> : hires or avails any services or any beneficiary of such service. \n\n

<u>Examples </u>: A goes to a doctor to get himself treated for a fracture. Here A is hiring the services of the doctor. Thus he is a consumer.\n\n

<u>Consumer Rights</u> :\n\n

Right to safety against hazardous goods and services\n\n
Right to be informed about quality, quantity, purity, standard, price\n\n
Right to choose from a variety at competitive prices\n\n
Right to be heard\n\n
Right to seek redressal\n\n
Right to consumer education\n\n-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</string><string name="title_activity_number_four">Complain</string><string name="def"><u>Consumer</u> :1.2 Section 2(d) of the Consumer Protection Act says that consumer means any person who does the following: \n\n

(i) buys any goods for a consideration which has been paid or promised or partly paid and partly promised, or under any system of deferred payment, and includes any user of such goods other than the person who buys such goods for consideration paid or promised or partly paid or partly promised, or under any system of deferred payment when such use is made with the approval of such person, but does not include a person who obtains such goods for resale or for any commercial purpose; or \n\n

(ii) hires or avails of any services for a consideration which has been paid or promised or partly paid and partly promised, or under any system of deferred payment, and includes any beneficiary of such services other than the person who hires or avails of the services for consideration paid or promised, or partly paid and partly promised, or under any system of deferred payment, when such services are availed of with the approval of the first mentioned person. \n\n


<u>Consumer of goods</u> - The provision reveals that a person claiming himself as a consumer of goods.\n\n

<u>Consumer of services </u>- A person is a consumer of services provided by other.\n\n

<u>Unfair Trade Practice</u> - The Act says that, "unfair trade practice" means a trade practice which, for the purpose of promoting the sale, use or supply of any goods or for the provison of any service, adopts any unfair method or unfair or deceptive practice. \n\n

<u>Restrictive Trade Practice</u> - Section 2(1)(nn) of the Act provides that, \'restrictive trade practice\' means "any trade practice which requires a consumer to buy, hire or avail of any goods or, as the case may be, services as a condition precedent for buying, hiring or availing of other goods or services".\n\n

<u>Goods</u> : Every kind of movable property other than actionable claims and money; and includes stock and shares, growing crops, grass, and things attached to or forming part of the land which are agreed to be severed before sale or under the contract of sale. \n\n

<u>Defect</u> : Section 2(1)(f) of the Act provides that, "defect" means any fault, imperfection or shortcoming in the quality, quantity, potency, purity or standard which is required to be maintained by or under any law of the time being in force under any contract, express or implied or as is claimed by the trader in any manner whatsoever in relation to any goods. \n\n

<u>Service</u> : Section 2(1)(o) of the Act provides that "service" means service of any description which is made available to potential users and includes the provision of facilities in connection with banking, financing, insurance, transport, processing, supply of electrical or other energy, board or loading or both, housing construction, entertainment, amusement or the purveying of news or other information, but does not include the rendering of any service free of charge or under a contract of personal service. \n\n

<u>Trader</u> : Section 2(1)(q) of the Act says that ‘trader’ means any person who sells or distributes any goods for sale and includes the manufacturer thereof, and where such goods are sold or distributed in package form, includes the packer thereof. \n\n

<u>Manufacturer</u>: Manufacturer is a person who either himself manufactures goods, or assemble any goods manufactured by others, or puts his own mark or trade mark on the goods manufactured by others. \n\n ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
    
</string><string name="title_activity_number_three">Consumer</string><string name="title_activity_number_two">Definition</string><string name="title_activity_number_six">References</string><string name="app_name">Consumer Protection Rights</string><string name="title_activity_number_one">Introduction</string><string name="hello_world">Hello world!</string></file><file path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\values\styles.xml" qualifiers=""><style name="AppBaseTheme" parent="android:Theme.Holo.Light.NoActionBar.Fullscreen">
        <!--
            Theme customizations available in newer API levels can go in
            res/values-vXX/styles.xml, while customizations related to
            backward-compatibility can go here.
        -->
    </style><style name="AppTheme" parent="AppBaseTheme">
        <!-- All customizations that are NOT specific to a particular API-level can go here. -->
    </style></file><file path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\values-sw720dp-land\dimens.xml" qualifiers="sw720dp-land-v13"><dimen name="activity_horizontal_margin">128dp</dimen></file><file path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\values-v11\styles.xml" qualifiers="v11"><style name="AppBaseTheme" parent="android:Theme.Holo.Light">
        <!-- API 11 theme customizations can go here. -->
    </style></file><file path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\main\res\values-v14\styles.xml" qualifiers="v14"><style name="AppBaseTheme" parent="android:Theme.Holo.Light.DarkActionBar">
        <!-- API 14 theme customizations can go here. -->
    </style></file></source><source path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\build\generated\res\rs\debug"/><source path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\build\generated\res\resValues\debug"/></dataSet><dataSet config="debug" generated-set="debug$Generated"><source path="C:\Users\user\Desktop\Android_Nano_Workspace\ConsumerProtectionRights\app\src\debug\res"/></dataSet><mergedItems/></merger>